Guide to the Dutton Family Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Dutton Family Papers
1800-1880
RG 63
Yale University Divinity School Library
9
(18 boxes)
The collection is valuable for the documentation it provides concerning a New Haven area clergy family during the period 1800 to 1880. Daily events and family relationships are revealed in substantive family correspondence. Of particular interest are Samuel Dutton's notebooks from his student days at Yale. The bulk of the collection is comprised of manuscript sermons written by Aaron and Samuel Dutton during their pastorates in Guilford and New Haven. These sermons touch on topics such as slavery, the Civil War, "Millerism", temperance and immigration. The sermons span the careers of both Duttons, who were known for their abolitionist stances, and thus provide an opportunity for tracing the development of their thought over a number of years. Aaron Dutton was born in Watertown, Connecticut on May 21, 1780. He served as minister of the First Congregational Church in Guilford, Connecticut from 1806 until 1842, at which time he resigned due to the dissension in the congregation regarding his abolitionist stance. In 1843, he went to Iowa in service of the American Home Missionary Society. He died in New Haven in 1849. His son, Samuel William Southmayd Dutton was born in Guilford, Connecticut on March 14, 1814. After receiving his Bachelor of Arts degree from Yale in 1833, he held positions as teacher, tutor, rector, minister (North Church, New Haven, Connecticut), publisher and editor. He was a noted champion of the antislavery cause. He died in Millbury, Massachusetts in 1866.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1780 May 21 Born in Watertown, Ct.
1803 B.A., Yale
1803-1804 Preceptor of Woodstock Academy, then pursued study of theology under Timothy Dwight
1805 Licensed to preach
1806 Married Dorcas Southmayd. Their children were:Mary Dutton (1807-1887), Dorcas Southmayd Dutton Gilbert (1810-1849), Thomas Dutton (1812-1885), Samuel William Southmayd Dutton (1814-1866), Aaron Rice Dutton (1816-1885), John Southmayd Dutton (1818-1834), Anna Dutton (1820-1831), Matthew Henry Dutton (1822-1841)
1806-1842 Minister of First Congregational Church, Guilford. Besides his pastoral duties he also prepared many young men for college.
1825-1849 Member of Yale Corporation
1842 Resigned from position in Guilford, due to dissension in congregation regarding his abolitionist stance. The party which stood by him formed the Third Congregational Church of Guilford in November, 1843.
1843 Went to Iowa in service of American Home Missionary Society. He was invited to the pastoral charge of the church in Burlington, capital of the IowaTerritory. Illness prevented him from accepting the postion.
1849 Died in New Haven
Biographical / Historical
1814 Mar 14 Born in Guilford, Ct., son of Aaron and Dorcas Southmayd Dutton
1833 B.A., Yale
1833-1834 Taught at Mount Hope College, Baltimore, Md.
1834 Rector of Hopkins Grammar School, New Haven
1836-1838 Tutored at Yale and pursued theological studies
1838 Married Harriet Waters, who died in 1864; daughter of Asa Waters of Millbury, Ma.
1838-1866 Minister at North Church, New Haven, Ct. Was a noted champion of the antislavery cause
1842 Published A History of the North Church in New Haven
1843 New Englander established, of which Dutton was an associate editor; contributed 46 articles
1865 D.D., Brown University
1866 Jan Died in Millbury, Ma.
The discourse delivered at his funeral by the Rev. Leonard Bacon has been published. A sketch of his life appeared in the Congregational Quarterly for April, 1866.
Scope and Contents
I. Correspondence
II. Notebooks and diaries
III. Writings
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia
This collection is valuable for the documentation it provides concerning a New Haven area clergy family during the period 1800 to 1880. Daily events and family relationships are revealed in substantive family correspondence. Letters were most often exchanged when a family member had left the New Haven area to live in the Midwest. Mary Dutton, daughter of Aaron, for example, lived in Cincinnati, Ohio for a number of years. Letters exchanged with her parents reveal a conflict between her desire to continue her work there and her parents' desire to have their daughter living at home. Mary eventually returned to Connecticut and headed a girls' school in New Haven. The general correspondence in the collection is not extensive but includes letters from Charles Beecher, George Edward Day, and Increase Tarbox.
The notebooks and diaries of Series II highlight various facets of the lives of Mary and Samuel Dutton. Of particular interest are Samuel's notebooks from his student days at Yale. Notes on sermons preached in the Yale College Chapel are included, as well as class notes. Pocket diaries of Samuel Dutton for the years 1861 to 1864 are available. A series of account books of Mary Dutton with Austin and Gilbert, grocers, provide interesting detail on New Haven life during the period 1855 to 1865.
The bulk of the collection is comprised of manuscript sermons written by Aaron and Samuel Dutton during their pastorates in Guilford and New Haven. These sermons touch on topics such as slavery, the Civil War, "Millerism," temperance, and immigration. The sermons span the careers of both Duttons and thus provide an opportunity for tracing the development of their thought over a number of years.
The writings other than sermons in Series III are also of interest. Those of Aaron Dutton include college compositions and "disputes" from his Yale years, essays on theological subjects, and drafts of articles on subjects such as slavery, Congregationalism, and missionary work. The writings of Samuel Dutton include college compositions, speeches delivered before the Linonian Society, an address delivered at the Yale Commencement of 1833, reviews of works by Horace Bushnell, and others. Historical information regarding the North Church in New Haven is available in an 1860 statement of Dutton to its United Society.
The personal items and memorabilia of Series IV include a portrait of Aaron Dutton and the memorial sermon preached at the funeral of Samuel Dutton's wife.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Notebooks and Diaries
III. Writings
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia
Church work; Congregationalism; Emigration and immigration; Missions; Sermons, American; Slavery; Temperance; Guilford (Conn.) -- Church history -- Sources; New Haven (Conn.) -- Church history -- Sources; New Haven (Conn.) -- History -- Sources; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Sermons; Clergy; Editors; Educators; Beecher, Charles, 1815-1900; Day, George Edward, 1815-1905; Dutton, Aaron, 1780-1849; Dutton, Samuel W. S. (Samuel William Southmayd), 1814-1866; Tarbox, Increase N. (Increase Niles), 1815-1888; Church of Christ (New Haven, Conn.); Congregational Home Missionary Society; First Congregational Church (Guilford, Conn.); Yale University
- Correspondence, Series I
  - Family Correspondence
    - Aaron Dutton
      - 1 ALS to son Aaron Rice, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - 2 ALS to son Samuel, 1843 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - 2 ALS to son Matthew, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - 14 ALS to daughter Mary, 1825-1843 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Dorcas (Southmayd) Dutton
      - 7 ALS to daughter Mary, 1833-1836 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Aaron Rice Dutton
      - 8 ALS to father, 1840-1847 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - 1 ALS to mother, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - 3 ALS to sister Dorcas, 1841,1846,1847 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - 15 ALS to brother Samuel, 1842-1865 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - 2 ALS to brother Thomas, 1840,1842 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - To sister Mary, 1833-1880 (Box 1, Folder 10-16)
    - Samuel William Southmayd Dutton
      - 2 ALS to father, 1833,1834 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - To sister Mary, 1833-1863 (Box 1, Folder 18-20)
      - 2 ALS to Harriet Waters, 1828,1838 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - 1 ALS to brother Samuel, 1849 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - 2 ALS to sister Mary, 1866 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Mary Dutton
      - 7 ALS to mother, 1834-1838 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - 1 ALS to brother Samuel, 1835 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - 2 ALS to brother Thomas, 1835 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - 1 ALS to brother John, 1834 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - 9 ALS to sister Dorcas, 1833-1836 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Edwin Randolph Gilbert (husband of daughter Dorcas)
      - 2 ALS to brother-in-law Samuel, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - 1 ALS to sister-in-law Mary, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - General Correspondence
    - Samuel William Southmayd Dutton
      - 2 ALS from L.G. Buckingham, 1841,1842 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - 2 ALS from William Carter, 1859 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - 1 ALS from William Chauvenet, 1841 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - 1 ALS to Rev. Dr. Cleaveland, 1856? (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - 2 ALS from J.I.T. Coolidge, 1858,1859 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - 1 ALS from O.K. Daggett, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - 5 ALS from George Edward Day, 1841-1844 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - 1 ALS from J. DeForest, 1857 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - 1 ALS from Jas. T. Dickinson, 1859 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - 1 ALS from L. Griggs, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - 1 ALS from J. Guernsey, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - 1 ALS from Horace James, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Extract of ALS to Horace Mann, 1842 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - 1 ALS from Alphonso Taft, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - 18 ALS from Increase N. Tarbox, 1844-1847 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - 1 ALS from Asa Turner, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Harriet Waters Dutton
      - 2 ALS from Increase N. Tarbox, 1845 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Mary Dutton
      - 1 ALS from Charles Beecher, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - 1 ALS from Sara I. Gillette, 1838 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - 1 ALS from O.P. Hubbard, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - 1 ALS from M. Peters, 1833 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - 1 ALS from Mary Thomas, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Edwin Randolph Gilbert
      - 1 ALS to W.B. Clarke, 1866 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Notebooks and Diaries, Series II
  - Samuel William Southmayd Dutton
    - Pocket diaries, 1861- 1864 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Index of subjects, 1835 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Notebook of sermons in Yale College Chapel by Dr. Fitch and others (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Notebook containing subjects for compositions, orations, etc., questions for debate, passages of poetry and of prose, missionary subjects, texts, and notes on European history, 1832 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Notebooke recording visits with parishioners, 1855,1860 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Mary Dutton
    - Account and note book, ca.1829-1831 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Account record regarding payment received for music lessons, 1858-1868 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Account books with Austin and Gilbert, grocers in New Haven, 1855-1865 (Box 3, Folder 37,38)
- Writings, Series III
  - Aaron Dutton
    - Sermons
      - Sermons, 1812 Feb-1813 Mar (Box 3, Folder 39-41)
      - Sermons, 1813 Apr-1826 (Box 4, Folder 42-47)
      - Sermons, 1827-1831 (Box 5, Folder 48-52)
      - Sermons, 1832-1838 (Box 6, Folder 53-59)
      - Sermons, 1839-1843, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 60-62)
      - fragments (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - Other writings:
      - College compositions and "disputes", ca.1800-1803 (Box 7, Folder 64,65)
      - Notes on sermons and lectures of Dr. Dwight (Box 7, Folder 66)
      - Essays on theological subjects, ca. 1803-1804 (Box 8, Folder 67,68,69,70)
      - Notes for sermons, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 71)
      - Drafts of articles - on slavery, on Congregationalism, on report of American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, re. Prof. Bush's view of the resurrection, 1846, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 72)
  - Samuel William Southmayd Dutton
    - Sermons
      - Sermons, 1837-1840 (Box 9, Folder 73-79)
      - Sermons, 1841-1843 (Box 10, Folder 80-85)
      - Sermons, 1844-1846 (Box 11, Folder 86-90)
      - Sermons, 1846-1848 (Box 12, Folder 91-95)
      - Sermons, including "An Address at the Funeral of Hon. David Daggett" (1851), 1849-1851 (Box 13, Folder 96-101)
      - Sermons, 1852-1854 (Box 14, Folder 102-108)
      - Sermons, 1855-1857 (Box 15, Folder 109-114)
      - Sermons, 1858-1861 (Box 16, Folder 115-121)
      - Sermons, 1862-1866 (Box 17, Folder 122-127)
      - fragments, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 128)
    - Other writings:
      - College compositions, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 129)
      - Speeches delivered before Linonian Society, 1832-1833 (Box 18, Folder 130)
      - "Colloquy on the Utility of Philosophical Criticism", delivered at Yale Commencement, 1833 (Box 18, Folder 131)
      - Statement directed to the United Society of North Church regarding possibility of SWSD's dismission, 1860? (Box 18, Folder 132)
      - Addresses for use in ordinations and installations (Box 18, Folder 133)
      - Notes and essays on theological subjects (Box 18, Folder 134, 135)
      - Reviews of works by Horace Bushnell, Jeremiah Day, Orville Dewy, and Henry Tappan, 1839-1864 (Box 18, Folder 136)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1864; Series IV
  - Address at funeral of Harriet Dutton by L. G. Buckingham, 1864 (Box 18, Folder 137)
  - Portrait of Aaron Dutton (reproduction) (Box 18, Folder 137)